Pauline Breustedt collection, Inclusive: circa 1917-1973, undated, Bulk: 1922-1959, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Pauline Breustedt collection
Inclusive: circa 1917-1973, undated, Bulk: 1922-1959, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
1832
Breustedt, Pauline
3 document boxes 2 oversize boxes
The Pauline Breustedt collection documents the life and travels of a Waco resident from 1917 to 1969. Items of interest include scrapbooks, post cards, news clippings, and photographs of her personal interests, acting career, and travels.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Pauline Breustedt was born 1898 July 3 in Waco, Texas, to William and Jean Breustedt. Pauline’s early education was in Waco schools followed by Miss Wright’s School in Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, and Smith College in Northampton, Massachusetts, from which she graduated cum laude. Pauline also attended finishing school in France.
As a member of Waco’s social elite during the 1920s, Breustedt was mentioned in the society pages as she regularly visited friends and family in New York and New Orleans. In 1923 she was crowned Waco Cotton Palace Queen. During this time, she also traveled throughout the United States and to such places as Europe, Cuba, and South America.
Throughout her schooling, Pauline was a regular on the stage, performing in shows at Miss Wright’s and Smith College. She obtained her first professional acting credit as an understudy on Broadway and in 1925 joined the Stuart Walker Company in Cincinnati, Ohio. She spent three seasons with the company and performed regularly in Cincinnati and Dayton, Ohio.
In 1936, Breustedt became a founding member of the Service League of Waco, now known as the Junior League of Waco, Inc. In that same year, Pauline began a five-month world tour and visited destinations in Europe, Asia, and Central America.
While Pauline Breustedt spent much time away for school, work, and leisure travel, she always claimed Waco as home. In 1977 she participated in an oral history project with the Junior League of Waco and the Baylor Institute of Oral History on the Women of Waco. Pauline Breustedt died April 2, 1978, and is buried at Oakwood Cemetery in Waco, Texas.
Scope and Content
The Pauline Breustedt collection documents her life and travels. A related oral history interview can be found at the Baylor University Institute for Oral History.
The General series includes newspaper and magazine clippings highlighting Pauline’s interests in fashion, politics, royalty, book reviews, theatre, and other subjects. Also included are invitations to several social events, travel brochures, and correspondence. The correspondence includes a type-written letter of invitation, signed by Dr. A.J. Armstrong, to the opening of the Armstrong Browning Library at Baylor University.
The Post Cards and Photographs series includes portraits of Pauline Breustedt and photographs of a farmhouse in Flatonia, Texas. The house was the childhood home of her mother, Jean. Postcards are of two sorts, those received by Pauline and Jean from various friends and family and a collection of blank cards. She likely collected the blank cards on her travels as some are consistent with her lifelong scrapbook.
The Scrapbooks series includes books of personal as well as family interests. The largest scrapbook is a cumulative lifetime album that begins with trip to Hawaii and includes travel photos from a world tour and vacations and visits with family and friends throughout Breustedt’s lifetime. Personal interest books document her life including her relationships with friends such as Prince George of Russia and Eleanor Cameron of Waco, Texas, and ongoing interest in the theater through programs and collected reviews of plays she attended in Waco, Dallas, New York, and London. Clippings included are representative of her interests in fashion, books, politics, and royalty; Pauline’s personal commentary can be seen throughout. There is also a post card album of international and local destinations, however, it is unclear if these were acquired by Pauline on her travels or given to her by others.
Arrangement
The collection was previously organized based on item type and had a box listing. This arrangement was observed while implementing new series and more detailed processing. The collection is now arranged in three series; Series I: General, Series II: Post Cards and Photographs, and Series III: Scrapbooks.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1832. Acquired 1978-09-21
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. “Pauline Breustedt.” Memorial #103796038. Databases. Accessed 2020 September 10.
“History.” Junior League of Waco, Inc. Accessed 2020 August 21.
“Lower Merion & Narberth: Five Schools and Libraries.” Lower Marion Historical Society. Accessed 2020 September 9.
Interview of Pauline Breustedt by Janelle Easley. Junior League of Waco, 1977 February 23. Transcript, Baylor University Institute for Oral History, Waco, Texas. Accessed 2020 September 11.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Breustedt, Pauline.
Subjects
Postcards.; Travel.; Voyages and travels.; Women in the theater.; Women travelers.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- General, 1921-1959, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The General series, dated 1921-1959, includes clippings, travel brochures, invitations, items documenting Breustedt’s personal interests, and limited correspondence. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Travel Brochures, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Waco Chamber of Commerce News Publications, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1922-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invitations and Correspondence, 1928-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal Interests, 1939-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Post Cards and Photographs, 1948-1973, undated; 2
  The Post Cards and Photographs series has several undated items, but also includes items dated 1948-1973. Contents include limited personal photographs and numerous post cards from various world-wide destinations. The series is arranged in alphabetical order and in excellent condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print; Portrait photograph; Postcards
  - Photographs: Farmhouse, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs: General, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs: Pauline, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs: Portrait Photo of Pauline, undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Post Cards: General, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Post Cards: Europe and Asia, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Post Cards: Italy, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Post Cards: Jamaica and Bali, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Post Cards: Spain, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Post Cards: Texas, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Post Cards: To Jean Breustedt (Mrs. William), 1948-1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Post Cards: To Others, circa 1955-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Post Cards: To Pauline, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Post Cards: To Pauline, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Post Cards: To Pauline, 1960-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Post Cards: United States (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Post Cards: United States (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Scrapbooks, circa 1917-1969, undated; 3
  The Scrapbooks series is dated circa 1917-1969 and documents the personal interests of Pauline Breustedt. Scrapbooks include photographs, news clippings, programs, post cards, local and personal interests. Each book has been assigned a title based on its content. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  Photograph album; Postcards
  - House Plans and Ideas for Dr. and Mrs. Maurice Barns, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Post Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Contemporary Women in Theatre, circa 1917 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Personal and Family Interests, 1928-1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Career, Travel, and Personal Interests, 1922-1930 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Personal Interests, circa 1934-1938 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Travel, 1936-1969 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 1)